<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Objections against the taking of the engagement answered. Or, Some scruples of conscience, which a godly minister in Lancashire did entertain against the taking of the engagement. Resolved by J.D. wherein the chief mistakes of weak consciences, about the matter of the engagement, are in a friendly way discovered, and rectified by scripture-grounds and right reason; and published for the satisfaction of others, who may be scrupled in the same kind.</title>
            <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81926</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2876</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E608_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205922</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865146</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865146</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117383</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81926)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117383)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 93:E608[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Objections against the taking of the engagement answered. Or, Some scruples of conscience, which a godly minister in Lancashire did entertain against the taking of the engagement. Resolved by J.D. wherein the chief mistakes of weak consciences, about the matter of the engagement, are in a friendly way discovered, and rectified by scripture-grounds and right reason; and published for the satisfaction of others, who may be scrupled in the same kind.</title>
                  <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Clowes, for Richard Woodnothe at the Star under St. Peters Church in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: John Dury.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug. 3d,"; the author's initials have been extended to read J.D"ury".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Act for subscribing the Engagement.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117383:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OBJECTIONS AGAINST The taking of the ENGAGEMENT Anſwered.</p>
            <p>OR, Some ſcruples of Conſcience, which a godly Miniſter in Lancaſhire did entertain againſt the taking of the ENGAGEMENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved by</hi> J. D.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN The chief miſtakes of weak Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, about the matter of the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are in a friendly way diſcovered, and rectified by <hi>Scripture</hi>-grounds and right reaſon; and publiſhed for the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of others, who may be ſcrupled in the ſame kind.</p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> John Clowes, <hi>for</hi> Richard Woodnothe, <hi>at the Star under St.</hi> Peters <hi>Church in</hi> Cornhill, 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:117383:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117383:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have delay'd writing for a time, in that I have been uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain whether I ſhould come to <hi>London</hi> or no; but now at the laſt reſolving to wait a while before I come, do make bold to preſent my humble thankfulneſs for your former kindnes ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me: I have been much perplexed in mind concerning the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, and ſtill am; by which means my maintenance is, and hath for a ſeaſon been withheld. Thoſe ſcruples which I ſtick at, I ſhall make bold to acquaint you with, and they are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> The late Government voted down was in it ſelf lawful, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and good, and no evil ever yet did appear to me in the power, but only in the perſons who did exerciſe that power,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21.</note> which was no ſufficient ground of change, and it is not ſafe to meddle in it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> To that ſaid Government I am bound by many ſolemn and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Tyes, to maintain it in my place, not only in the ſubſtance and main parts of it, but alſo in the form and circumſtance thereof, and thoſe ſaid obligations are not meerly civil and humane, but ſacred and divine, and above the abſolution of any earthly power.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> I conceive it unlawful to engage againſt the undoubted rights of any man. I ſuppoſe there may be found ſuch lawful Heirs of the Crown, as have not any wayes forfeited their rights, and alſo great Intereſts and Priviledges which mary innocent Peers of this Land may fairly challenge, which they have not loſt by their miſcarriage, Treaſon or Rebellion.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> I cannot be ſatisfied, but that the liberty of the free-born Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, is by that means much infringed in this late ſettlement and conſtitution. <hi>1.</hi> In that many of the innocent and faithful Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, the Repreſentatives of the people, were at the voting of this new eſtabliſhment, thruſt out and debarred the Houſe, which makes it ſeem rather a combination or confederacy, then a lawful conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for if a people have liberty in any thing, certainly it is to chuſe
<pb facs="tcp:117383:3"/>their Governors and Government. <hi>2.</hi> The ſubſcription is forced upon us, under the penalties of out-lawing and fining, ſo that this power, are our abſolute Lords, which is that heavy yoak that we have fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and fought againſt.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> I conſider, if men at their inition and inſtallment will walk ſo arbitrarily, and domineere with ſo high a hand, what will they do, (may we expect) when they come to a full ſettlement, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all the people of the Nation?</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> The grieving and troubling the hearts and Conſciences not of looſe, perverſe and ſeditious, but of grave, ſober, pious and peaceable men, is made nothing of, but they are trampled upon, and wholly neglected, whilſt many Atheiſts, Cavaliers, and baſe wretches that will take the Engagement, are imbraced, priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and reſpected.</p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch dear Sir, are the troubles of my heart, which I make bold to expreſs thus plainly, not doubting of your favour in conſtruing my harſh and too high phraſes, and ove-rbold expreſſions; only I follow this as the ſafeſt way to ſatisfaction and reſolution, hoping that the Lord will of his goodneſs, ſtir you up and direct you to ſatisfie me; or candidly to think of and bear with me: Sir, your loving invitation and incouragement hath made me thus bold to trouble you; and as for thoſe other buſineſſes I formerly mentioned, I conceive little can be done, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>Dated <date>
                  <hi>9. May. 1650.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117383:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>OBJECTIONS</hi> againſt the taking of the ENGAGEMENT Anſwered.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hope you have received my former, written the 28. of <hi>May;</hi> wherein I ſent you back the <hi>Petition</hi> of your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, with ſome inſtructions how you ſhould do, to get your buſineſs ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected? Now I ſhall endeavour to offer ſomething to your conſideration towards the ſatisfaction of thoſe ſcruples which you have ſent me; for which you have not been able to take the <hi>Engagement:</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> who alone is the Father of lights, and knowes the capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all Mens Conſciences; inſtruct us in the truth, and by it grant us that quietneſs and reſt of ſpirit, which may fit us, for the performance of all righteouſneſs and dutifulneſs with joy: he alone can teach us to profit, and lead the wearied ſole to reſt; we may ſuggeſt to one another, that wherein according to our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117383:4"/>apprehenſion is truth, ſo far as it appears ſo to us; but to ſeal up that truth and perſwade the heart of it, is the work of the ſpirit of <hi>God</hi> alone, whom our heavenly <hi>Father,</hi> by the mouth of his own <hi>Son,</hi> hath promiſed to give to them that ask him. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. We may therefore with full aſſurance crave this ſpirit, not only for our ſelves, but each for other; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps herein we may do one another better ſervice then in ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting our notions to each other. Yet becauſe we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded not only to ask by way of requeſt, but to ſeek and knock at the Gates of Heaven,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7.</note> by way of endeavour: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us do the one, and not neglect the other, and if it ſhall be the Lords will, that by the diſcovery of thoſe things which give me ſatisfaction in that whereat you are ſcrupled, you ſhall find more light then you now have, and cauſe of ſatisfaction and reſt to your mind therein, I ſhall rejoyce at it, and bleſs <hi>God</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>Give me leave therefore to diſcover unto you, the grounds for which my Conſcience ought not to be troubled at the things which you ſcruple ſo much at; for you are brought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by into many inconveniences and ſtraits, which I conceive you have caſt your ſelf into, for want of due conſideration of thoſe Rules, which would have ſteered your courſe clear from thoſe <hi>Rocks</hi> and <hi>Quick-ſands</hi> whereinto you are fallen.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Scruple, The former Government was in it ſelf good and not alterable.</note>The firſt ſcruple you make is this. <hi>The late Government</hi> (ſay you) <hi>voted down, was in it ſelf lawful, wholſome and good: and no evil ever yet did appear to me in the power, but only in the perſons who did exerciſe that power, which was no ſufficient ground of Change, and it is not ſafe to meddle in it.</hi> Prov. 24.21.</p>
            <p>Now this doth not trouble me at all, &amp; I ſuppoſe needs not to be a matter of Conſcience to you; that is; you need not to charge the conſequence which you mention here upon your Conſcience;<note place="margin">The Anſwer ſhewes</note> for although I ſhould think as you do, that the late Government now voted down, was in it ſelf lawful; yet it doth not follow therefore,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.12. <hi>&amp; Chap.</hi> 10.23.</note> that it is ſtill moſt expedient for the publick ſtate. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith in two places, that all things are lawful for him, but all things are not expedient. Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the Conſcience of an intelligent Chriſtian is not bound to every thing which may appear lawful (for no material acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117383:4"/>can be named but in ſome ſence it is lawful) but that a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſideration muſt be had of every thing,<note place="margin">That things obliging Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, muſt be not only good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to us.</note> before we faſten it, as an obligation upon our Conſcience: the conſideration of the expediency of a thing muſt caſt the ballance, as to the inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of Conſcience into a buſineſs: and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> defines this expediency or inexpediency by two things, one in reſpect of our ſelves, another in reſpect of our Neighbour. In reſpect of our ſelves it is not expedient that we ſhould be brought under the power of every thing which in it ſelf is lawful; as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> ſaith: <hi>All things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought under the power of any.</hi> To be brought under the power of any thing is to make it ſo neceſſary to us, that we cannot forgo it, or think that we cannot pleaſe God without it. Now the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth teach us, that no outward thing ſhould have any ſuch power over our ſpirits, as to bring our Conſcience into ſuch a ſubjection. Nor <hi>Paul, nor Apollo, nor Cephas, nor the World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22.</note> 
               <hi>nor life, nor death, nor things preſent, nor things to come,</hi> ſhould bring us under this yoke; but we ought to account all ours, that is under our power, as we are ſubordinate in reference to Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, unto <hi>God</hi> alone in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> it followes then, that whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver things be preſent with us in this life, and how lawful ſoever they may be in themſelves; that yet my Conſcience is not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to be ſubjected to their power, then as I ſtand under God in Chriſt; and as thoſe things are expedient and ſubſervient to that ſubordination in reſpect of our Neighbour; if any thing edifie not, it is determined not to be expedient, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.23. although then a thing may be lawful, wholſome, and good in it ſelf; yet if I find it not expedient for edification, I am not bound to uſe it, but may leave it, and make uſe of ſomething elſe which I ſhall judge moſt edifying. If therefore God hath ſet my Conſcience free, ſo that I am not bound to any thing further then it is edifying ; it doth not at all follow, that becauſe I judge a thing lawful and good in it ſelf; that therefore I muſt needs chuſe it, and be ſubject to the power thereof without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deliberation: as for example, if it were abſolutely refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to me to ſettle what Government I will chuſe; whether <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical, Ariſtocratical,</hi> or <hi>Democratical;</hi> I muſt not oblige my ſelf in this choiſe only, to conſider what is lawful (for all theſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117383:5"/>are lawful,<note place="margin">What Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is to be counted moſt expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</note> good and wholſom forms in themſelves) but what is moſt expedient: and if I ſhould now ſpeak as a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> to tell you what I think expedient in the choiſe of any of theſe, I would tell you, that the Government which conſiſts moſt with the rational and orderly freedom of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Emergencies doth tend moſt unto the edification of the publick in all good things, is that which is to be choſen. therfore if in your unprejudiced thoughts you wil contemplate this Querie: you will not do amiſs, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by a <hi>King</hi> who having the ſole power, may not be controuled; or the Government by a <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Truſtees,</hi> who may have this ſame Power put in their hands, be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to <hi>Chriſtian</hi> freedom and publick edification, yea or no? I know what I could ſay to this Querie, if I were an abſolute lawful Judge of a publick concernment of this nature: but now I not being free to make my choiſe of Government; but it being wholly in the hand of publick Truſtees, to manage all publick affairs for me, ſo that I muſt be concluded by them in ſuch concernments; ſeeing (I ſay) I am under a power where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I owe ſubjection,<note place="margin">Who is to be the Judge of the expedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and it is at all times expedient that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men ſhould be under the power of ſome Government, to whom the management of publick affairs is to be committed: therefore I muſt not make my ſelf a judge how expedient or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expedient the reſolutions are, which they ſettle concerning the way of Government in the State, (for that is their proper calling to conſider and not mine) and if I may not judge either way, it is clear that my Conſcience cannot be brought under the power of their reſolutions either way; but it is always free for me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>God,</hi> in civil affairs, to ſubmit unto their changeable deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, and not to oppoſe the orders which they ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to make therein:<note place="margin">And what uſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ought to make of changes therein.</note> my meaning is, that as all other outward things, ſo the reſolutions and determinations of my Magiſtrates are min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and that it is free for me to make uſe of them ſo as is moſt expedient for publick edification: if then a change fall out in the Government amongſt them, and they judge it either expedient or neceſſary, to alter that form where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no evil yet ever appeared to me; yet by this, my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is not obliged either to reſiſt them becauſe they alter what
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117383:5"/>ſeems not evil to me, or not to yield unto them to make the beſt of what they have done, ſo far as may be edifying in my way; for I am bound in Conſcience to take all things as they fall in my way, and to make uſe of them freely to the end of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification: if therefore they in their places make changes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though as to the outward man I am concluded by them to ſtand under the ſame; yet as to my Conſcience, I am not in ſubjection to ſuch changes, nor obliged to make my ſelf a judge, and to determine whether the changes which they make be lawful or unlawful, expedient or inexpedient to the State, that I muſt leave to God and to them, and to the event to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine. From all which this will follow, that if I ſuffer my thoughts to be intangled into this judicature, as into a matter of Conſcience neceſſary for me to determine, I then looſe my freedom which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath given me: for he doth not oblige my Conſcience to be under the power of any ſuch thing in his ſervice; for whether the determinations of ſuperiour powers in State-affairs, be right or wrong, I am alwayes the ſame man, free to make a good uſe of them; ſo far as they can lawfully and with expediency be referred unto edification. If therefore I ſhould argue as you do, <hi>Monarchy is lawful in it ſelf, I never ſaw any evil in it, but only in the perſons that exerciſe it, and the mal-adminiſtration of a power is no ſufficient ground to change the power it ſelf; and therefore the change which hath been made of late is not warrantable, and ſo conclude that I am not bound to do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny duty to the preſent Government:</hi> if (I ſay) I ſhould argue thus, I ſhould find my ſelf (upon a narrower ſearch) to be in a deep ſhare, and that in ſeveral reſpects. Firſt,<note place="margin">What the fallacies are, upon which this ſcruple doth riſe.</note> by bringing the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of State as a yoke upon my Conſcience, as if it were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power thereof, further then to be ſubject in lawful things unto the powers which are over me. Secondly, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my ſelf a ſupream judge of the management of Affairs committed to other men. And thirdly, by ſuch invalid reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings as theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If the Government to a <hi>Monarch</hi> be lawful in it ſelf, <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> it was not expedient at this time to be voted down in this State.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:117383:6"/>2. If I never ſaw any evil in the power of a <hi>Monarch;</hi> but only in the perſon: <hi>Ergo</hi> it is not lawful for a Parliament to change that power; or expedient for the publick good that it ſhould be changed, or for me to ſubmit unto the change there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and obey ſuch as are over me.</p>
            <p n="3">If there is no evil in the power, but only in the perſons that exerciſe it; <hi>Ergo</hi> there was no ſufficient ground in theſe emergencies to change that power.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21. <hi>My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with thoſe that are given to change. Ergo</hi> I may not engage to be faithful to the powers which are over me, and to the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> wherein I live, if it be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed without a <hi>King.</hi> If (I ſay) I ſhould argue thus, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a way of reaſoning, ſuffer my Conſcience to be entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, perplexed, and ſuſpended in matters of clear duty, ſo that I ſhould not dare to make uſe of all humane changes without ſcruple, to the ends of ſpiritual and bodily advantages for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good and ſafety; then I would judge my ſelf under the power of theſe things by unadviſedneſs; and would reſolve to ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>All things indeed are lawful; but I will not be under the power of any,</hi> and ſo ſet my ſelf at liberty from all ſuch intanglements of my Conſcience. The place of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> is a clear rule for private men, not to meddle with deſignes of publick changes beyond their Calling: therefore whereever I find things eſtabliſhed in a State, or ſo far as I find them eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, I am bound to fear God and the King (the <hi>King</hi> is the power which is ſupream, and under God as his Vicegerent, whether it be in the hand of one man or of many) and am not bound to contribute to the unſettlement of a Government e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed,<note place="margin">The place of Scripture, Prov. <hi>24.21.</hi> opened.</note> which is the deſign of ſome who reſpect neither <hi>God</hi> nor the <hi>King,</hi> and perhaps of ſome others alſo, who might be governed by higher principles then either <hi>Cavaliers</hi> or <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers,</hi> who are equally addicted to the extremities of changes; but when a change is made, and a State ſetled under it, then not to acquieſce in it, in the fear of God &amp; of the power which is ſupream; but to ſeek for new changes in oppoſition to ſuch a ſettlement, is manifeſtly againſt this Rule of <hi>Solomon:</hi> for not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117383:6"/>to meddle with thoſe that are given to changes, I conceive is, not to have to do out of our calling with private plots tending to publick changes; but <hi>ex poſt facto,</hi> to do our duty in all good things to all men, and chiefly to ſuperiours, though they are eſtabliſhed after a change; I ſuppoſe is no wayes prohibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this place; and that is clearly your caſe, if you will but open your eyes to behold it, and this ſhall ſuffice to your firſt ſcruple. The ſecond is this:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Scruple, My Oaths bind me to the form of a Monarchical Government.</note>
               <hi>I am bound</hi> (ſay you) <hi>by many ſolemn and ſacred tyes, to the Government of a Monarch, to maintain it in my place; not only in the ſubſtance and main parts of it, but alſo in the form and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thereof: and thoſe ſaid obligations are not meerly civil and humane, but ſacred and divine, and above the abſolution of any earthly power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſhall ſay, that I was bound no leſs then you, to the Government of a <hi>Monarch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The anſwer ſhewes, that the former Oaths are not any more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging.</note> to maintain it and ſhew all fidelity to it ſo long as it was in being; but ſince it is no more in being amongſt us, I know no tye, (though never ſo ſolemn and ſacred at the making) that can bind me any more to it; for the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of all Oaths is only obſervable, whiles the matter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is in being: and this rule is undeniable, <hi>ſublatâ juramenti materiâ tollitur obligatio.</hi> I conceive therefore, that although when time was, I was bound to <hi>Monarchical Government,</hi> both to the ſubſtance, and to the ſetled form and circumſtances thereof, as they ſtood in Law; yet that now I am no more bound thereunto, becauſe <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> theſe tyes are unlooſed not by the abſolution of any earthly power, to pronounce the tye void, (which nevertheleſs hath alſo been done by the ſupream power of the Nation, when they declared the Government to be altered) but by the decree of Heaven, which hath providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, and <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> looſened the tyes by removing the late <hi>King</hi> and his Heirs from the legal capacity wherein they ſtood towards me formerly, that is, before this <hi>Parliament</hi> made it treaſon to make any more addreſſes to him, and before he was ſentenced for treaſon himſelf.</p>
            <p>Now that God hath a right by the changes of Government, to abſolve you from your ſacred tyes, I ſuppoſe you will not deny, and that he hath changed this Government, is undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117383:7"/>for without him it could not have been done, and he claims to himſelf the ſole power of changing Governments, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.17. And that the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> hath alſo a power according to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergencies to diſpoſe of the Government within it ſelf for its own ſafety, I think will not by you be denyed; and if by the changes which it hath power to make within it ſelf, as emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies require, the matter of your Oath be taken away, it is clear, that thereby the obligation is extinct. Above all this, I ſhall offer unto your conſideration, ſomething concerning the original of your ſacred tye; for the Oath which you took to maintain certain forms and circumſtances of Government (which in their own nature are alterable) was lawful to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by you;<note place="margin">What makes an Oath ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and binding as to Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> either becauſe the ſupream Authority that then was required it of you, and you ſaw no juſt cauſe to refuſe that which they required, or becauſe only you of your own accord did chuſe to take ſuch an Oath: I ſuppoſe you will not ſay the laſt, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Oath was only ſacred, becauſe you were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take it; for then all Oaths which any man ſhall be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take or make about State-affairs, may be as ſacred to him as yours was to you, and as juſtly taken by him, although they ſhould be quite contradictory unto yours, which is very abſurd; it will follow then, that the tye to thoſe things was ſacred; that is, it was lawful for you to be bound by an Oath to them only, becauſe the ſupream Authority which was over you, and had power to eſtabliſh thoſe forms and circumſtances of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did require ſuch an obligation from you, to engage you to be faithful thereunto, and if this is the only lawful original of ſuch a ſacred tye; then I ſay, that the diſſolution of that tye, may ariſe from the ſame power which did eſtabliſh it: he that hath power to oblige me to a form of his creating hath alſo power to abſolve me from that obligation. In old times and now alſo in ſome places, the Souldiers were wont to be obliged by Oath to ſerve their Commanders faithfully, till they ſhould be diſmiſſed: the <hi>Romans</hi> called this <hi>Sacramentum militare:</hi> Now he that might lawfully give them this Oath, might alſo abſolve them from it; and ſo it is in all obligations unto things, which in their own nature are not morally good, but good only <hi>ex in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituto legitimo:</hi> the power which gives them a being, may take
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117383:7"/>it from them; if therefore the ſupream power which now is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you, hath abſolved you from thoſe tyes, your voluntary continuance under them cannot make them any longer ſacred; no more then your voluntary taking an Oath at firſt to them, without the conduct of the authority which was over you, could have made your obligation lawful. I conceive then, that in things meerly civil and humane (that is of a changable na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as being ſubject to civil and humane Ordinances) your Oath cannot put a ſtronger tye upon you towards them, then their nature will bear; that is, you cannot be unalterably bound unto them; for if they ceaſe to be, you cannot ſtand ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged towards them; now that they do ceaſe to be is clear, and that they may ceaſe to be by the power which is over you, and by the Acts of divine providence abſolving Subjects from ſuch Oaths. If you will further ſee it made out, read the adjoyned an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the exercitation, particularly from pag. 20. till 25. and this ſhall alſo ſuffice for your ſecond ſcruple.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Scruple. The Kings Heirs have an undoubted right. Ergo I may not engage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. The Anſwer ſhewes. That no duty is <hi>per ſe</hi> a hinderance to any mans rights.</note>Your third ſcruple is, <hi>that you conceive it unlawful to engage againſt the undoubted rights of any man. I ſuppoſe</hi> (ſay you) <hi>there may be found ſuch lawful Heirs of the Crown, as have not any ways forfeited their right, and alſo great intereſts and priviledges, which many innocent Peers of this Land may fairly challenge, which they have not loſt by their miſcarriage, treaſon, or rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay with you, that I conceive it not lawful for me to engage againſt the undoubted rights of any: nor do I ſo by taking the <hi>Engagement,</hi> as it is a clear Duty; for by promiſing to be true and faithful to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as it is now eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed; and although that eſtabliſhment is without a <hi>King</hi> and Houſe of <hi>Lords,</hi> I do not engage againſt the right of any man; for no man can have any right to hinder me from this obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is the proper duty of a true Subject; nor can the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this to my underſtanding, be a hinderance <hi>per ſe,</hi> to any man to enjoy his rights. I ſay, that no duty <hi>per ſe,</hi> can be oppoſite to any thing that is right; but if it fall out <hi>per acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,</hi> that the doing of a thing which in it ſelf is good and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and a clear and neceſſary duty for publick ſafety, doth become the overthrow of ſome particular mens pretended rights; I muſt not be troubled thereat, but muſt leave the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117383:8"/>of all ſuch events unto Gods providence: not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not lawful for me to neglect a general and preſent duty, for the conſideration of any private intereſts, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily may be prejudged accidentally thereby; but alſo becauſe it is not lawful for me to make my ſelf a judge of theſe things which you call undoubted rights, and to determine the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted titles which any have or have not to a right of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or how far they may or may not lay a claim to it; it is not (I ſay) lawful for me in reference to the outward State; to become a Judge thereof; far leſs then ought I to make any ſuch judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, an engagement upon my Conſcience to ſuſpend it from a clear Duty, when it is required by Superiours, of whom only I can expect protection.</p>
            <p>As for the ſuppoſals which you make concerning the Heirs of the Crown, &amp; concerning the innocent Peers; I might allow my ſelf the liberty alſo to make ſuch ſuppoſals,<note place="margin">How far the conſideration of the Heirs and innocent Peers doth oblige the Conſcience to act or not to act duty with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and ſay with you, that poſſibly ſuch may be found, who have not forfeited their Rights, either by Treaſon or Rebellion; but what then? muſt I therefore conclude, becauſe ſuch perſons may poſſibly be found, that therefore I muſt in the interim not do my duty, to thoſe that have the power at preſent to protect me? muſt I, or may I conclude, becauſe thoſe perſons have not that which they challenge; that therefore I will not do what I owe to my ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours for common ſafety? this conſequence will not at all follow. But you will urge the point further and ſay, nay but if my Engagement to theſe ſuperiours, doth keep thoſe men from their Right; then am I acceſſary to the injuſtice which is done unto them. I anſwer firſt, my <hi>Engagement</hi> is only to a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and no ſuch <hi>Engagement</hi> can be <hi>per ſe,</hi> injurious to any, or acceſſary to any injuſtice in any: if accidentally it doth, or may fall out otherwiſe, I am not to anſwer for that, but remit it unto Gods providence. Secondly, divers things are ſuppoſed in this objection, which cannot be granted ſo, as to make them defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſentences of ſuch a nature, that your Conſcience muſt be engaged to act by them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That there are lawful Heirs of the Crown to be found, whoſe Right is not forfeited by Treaſon or Rebellion.</hi> This is a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence which I may perhaps think to be a truth, yet cannot as a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117383:8"/>Judge pronounce to be ſo. Secondly, that there are many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Peers, who have many Intereſts and Priviledges which they may fairly challenge, becauſe they have not forfeited them by their miſcarriage: this is alſo a ſentence which I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be a truth, but yet cannot judicially aſſert it no more then the former. Thirdly, it is ſuppoſed alſo, that becauſe there are many innocent Peers, who have many Intereſts and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges fairly to be challenged, that therefore they ought to have ſtill a ſeparate hand in the Government by a Houſe in <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> which is a conſequence for which I ſee no ground.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, on the other ſide, you ſuppoſe that they who now are in power, do injuſtice to the Heires who have not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited their Right to the Crown, by not ſetling the Crown up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one of them, and to the innocent Lords, by not letting them ſit to govern in a Houſe, which are ſentences no ways to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by Subjects of Superiours, and by non-judges of publick State-intereſts, nor in my opinion can they be made out to be truths, when we look upon them in the judgment of diſcretion: for although the Heirs and Peers may lay a claim to ſome rights in reſpect of former Cuſtoms; yet it followeth not, that if in theſe Emergencies former Cuſtoms be not obſerved, that therefore injuſtice is done unto them: for all Cuſtoms are in their nature to be ſubſervient to the publick good, and if they fall out to be at any time deſtructive thereunto, they ought to be changed, and if by the change thereof particular rights, or claims to rights are made void; that is no injuſtice in thoſe that alter the Cuſtom, although ſome particular perſons looſe that which at another time might be fairly challenged by them: all particular priviledges muſt yield to the publick ſafety; nor can any man fairly challenge any thing, which may prejudge pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſafety, and the powers that are in poſſeſſion, are the only Judges of that which is moſt conducible unto publick ſafety. The caſe of <hi>Henry</hi> 6. who was an uſurper, and of <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> who in full <hi>Parliament</hi> ſetting himſelf in the Chair of State, laid claim unto the Crown, is a clear deciſion of this matter: for though he made good his Title to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> yet after a long debate, it was enacted by the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> that the uſurper in poſſeſſion ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117383:9"/>the name and honour of a King, and the right Heir be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended from the enjoyment of his right; becauſe all particular rights muſt yield to publick welfare. This the Anſwer to the exercitation, doth quote out of <hi>Martins</hi> Hiſtory of the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> pag. 258. You ſee then how many ways theſe ſuppoſals of yours, whereupon you make conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences to trouble your Conſcience, are without ground; but now let me grant you that they are all of them truths, yet how will you make it out rationally, that they ought to be of ſuch importance to you,<note place="margin">Suppoſing the allegations to be valid, yet the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence not to engage to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of duty doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</note> that your Conſcience muſt be charged therewith as a Judge to determine them; and in caſe the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence which you pronounce thereof, be not executed, that you are bound to withdraw your ſelf from all dutiful relations to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the publick, and make your ſelf for ſuch conſiderations as theſe unprofitable to your flock, &amp; unſerviceable in the Miniſtry? I ſay, how will you be able to ſhew that this is a conſcionable courſe in you, although the grounds of your ſuppoſals were not ſo ſlight as they are, but as firm as any can be? to me I confeſs, although they might ſeem in the judgment of diſcretion unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable truths; yet becauſe I dare not for Conſcience ſake, make my ſelf a definitive Judge in the Caſe; and I am inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that my Conſcience is not to be under the Power of ſuch worldly changes, but that it is free for me allwayes to do my duty, though they be never ſo many, and ſo ſtrange: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will not be ſcrupled at theſe conſiderations, whereinto you have inconſiderately intangled your thoughts, which I think you are bound to ſhake off. And this ſhall ſuffice I hope alſo for the third ſcruple, whereunto I thought not at firſt to have ſaid half ſo much; but the deſire to clear the matter ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hath carried me on to be ſo large.</p>
            <p>Your fourth ſcruple is about the liberty of the Subject. You ſay thus,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Scruple. The liberties of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed, Ergo I muſt not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angage.</note> 
               <hi>I cannot be ſatisfied, but that the liberty of the free-born Engliſh is by that means much infringed in this late ſettlement and conſtitution.</hi> 1. <hi>In that many of the innocent and faithful Members, the repreſentatives of the people were at the voting of this new eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment thruſt out and debarred the Houſe, which makes it ſeem rather a Combination or Confederacy, then a lawful conſtitution; for if a People have liberty in any thing, certainly it is to chooſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117383:9"/>their Governors and Government.</hi> 2. <hi>The ſubſcription is forced up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, under the penalties of out-lawing and fining, ſo that this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er are our abſolute Lords, which is that heavy yoak that we have feared and fought againſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Anſwer ſhewes, That the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is not good.</note>Here your want of ſatisfaction in matters of liberty is the ground of your ſcruple; and your ſcruple is the cauſe why you will not engage to do good duties to the publick, under the preſent powers. To me this way of proceeding is not regular, for I conceive that no diſſatisfaction for any thing which I think amiſs in others, ought to take me off from my Reſolutions to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the publick, in things good and lawful to be done in my place. Nay I ſay the quite contrary, becauſe I am not ſatisfied in the ways of other men, and cannot ſee the clear grounds of their conſcionable dealing: I am bound ſo much the more to look to mine own Conſcience, and to keep to the duties which tend to maintain truth and peace towards all in my place, and to advance the publick welfare without partiality. If I ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend no good Office to any, but to ſuch in whoſe ways I am ſatisfied, I ſhould have little to do in the world as a Chriſtian: therefore I Command my ſpirit, either not to look to matters of diſſatisfaction in other men ſo deeply, as to make my ſelf a Judge of their ways, to the trouble of my Conſcience: or if I cannot avoid obſerving things diſſatisfactory to my ſpirit, which without any judicial ſearch offer themſelves clearly to my view; yet I ſuffer not thoſe impreſſions to work any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper upon me (ſo far as I can diſcern it) againſt thoſe whom I am bound to edifie, and to whom I muſt as a Servant of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> make my application for the beſt of things, to build them up in that which is ſpiritually and morally good.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">That we are not Judges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Liberties definitively, but only in the judgment of diſcretion.</note>As for the ſcruple it ſelf, whether the liberty of the free-born <hi>Engliſh,</hi> be yea or no, much infringed by this ſettlement and conſtitution; I ſhall no more in this then in other matters of the like nature take upon me to be a definitive Judge, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in the way of diſcretion I do judge of it, I am free; nay I am bound to make the beſt of it, for edification in my way: and not by reaſon of diſcontentedneſs, to obſtruct the liberty of my own ſpirit, in the duties of my Calling: The liberties of the free-born <hi>Engliſh,</hi> I am bound in my place to maintain, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117383:10"/>I had not been engaged by Oath, to declare my reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo to do: and what doth ſenſibly prejudge the ſame, I ought by lawful wayes within my ſphere endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move; but the proper work of my Calling is, to endeavour to bring all the free-born <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to be free-born in <hi>Sion,</hi> &amp; to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the glorious liberty of the Sons of God; whereby they ſhall be above theſe kinds of humane concernments, and yet not neglect the advantages which may redound by them to the Kingdom of God,<note place="margin">That whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters judge thereof in their Calling, they muſt make all free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to others through love.</note> which is to maintain all lawful freedom, ſo as to become therein a Servant to all men through love; for I know no priviledge that I have unto any freedom, either ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual or natural; but upon theſe terms which the Apoſtle hath taught me, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Brethren ye have been called unto liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, only uſe not liberty for an occaſion to the fleſh, but by love ſerve one another.</hi> Now if any pretence to liberty in mine own behalf or others, doth become an occaſion of diſcontentedneſs, of ſtrife of murmurings, and of ſullenneſs of ſpirit, whereby I am diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſed, ſo that I cannot ſerve all men freely in the duties of my Calling, then I am a transgreſſor of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Rule, and walk not according to the Law of liberty in the Kingdom of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> becauſe I ſuffer my Conſcience to be under the power of ſome other Relations to liberty, which I have not made ſubordinate unto the Relations of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs cannot be prejudged by any Oaths of an inferior concernment, according to the Rule, <hi>Quod in juramento ſemper jus ſuperioris intelligitur exceptum,</hi> and in our National Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, the obligation towards the maintaining of the Liberties of the Kingdom, is expreſſed to be only in order to our Calling and place. Now if we do not reckon our ſpiritual Calling as Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and our place in the Miniſtery to be the Rule, according to which that <hi>Engagement,</hi> and the endeavours which we owe to our civil freedoms, are to be managed, I know not what it is in our ſphere of the Miniſtery that can be meant by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction of that performance, to our Calling and place. I ſay then, that by the expreſs words of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> I am obliged not to make my plea for civil liberties, (if infringed) ſuch, as may prejudge my Chriſtian or Miniſterial liberties; as if it ſhould be lawful for me to forgo theſe, for want of ſatisfaction
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117383:10"/>in thoſe, or think it unlawful for me to make uſe of theſe when I conceive my ſelf deprived of thoſe. Now how far the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſworn to maintain their liberties are,<note place="margin">That theſe who are char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the infringment of liberties, plead for themſelves that which ſeems ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note> or are not deprived by this ſettlement of their civil freedom, if without preſuming above our line, we may endeavour to diſcern by looking with an indifferent aſpect upon that which is ſaid on both ſides; we will find a plea, which is not alltogether irrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal in the mouth of thoſe who are accuſed of the infringe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our liberties by this ſettlement. For firſt they will ſay, that according to the Truſt repoſed in them for publick ſafety and liberty, they have diſcharged their Conſcience in procuring this ſettlement, by which they intend to break the yoak which was prepared to have been put upon our necks, and to give all men, an equal intereſt into the welfare of the State, by a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi> conſtitution of <hi>Government,</hi> and that they have none other aim, but to ſettle by juſt Lawes, a ſafe and well ordered freedom throughout the whole Nation. Secondly, to the things wherein you are diſſatisfied: they will ſay that the Members debarred the Houſe by the Army were not innocent, in reſpect of their deſignes attempted, fomented and declared againſt the Army: and that they were not faithful to the proſecution of the Cauſe which they had undertaken; but fell from it to a royal Intereſt, without any aſſurance of ſafety and freedom left to the Subject in general, but more particularly to thoſe who had brought the publick enemies upon their knees, to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of their lives, who by the Treaty were not provided for; but rather a plot laid thereby to deſtroy them. Thirdly, they will ſay, that they who now ſit in <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſit there by the peoples free choiſe, and that therein the ground of all liberty is preſerved unto them; that they may ſend their repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives unto the <hi>Parliament;</hi> but to chuſe particular Governors to places, and the form of Government, otherwiſe then by their Truſtees met to that effect in <hi>Parliament,</hi> would not be a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty but a licentiouſneſs in any whoſoever ſhould attempt it. Fourthly, concerning the impoſing of the ſubſcription, under a penalty of out-lawing and fining; they will ſay that it is a fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental maxim of all <hi>Common-wealths</hi> that allegiance and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117383:11"/>muſt anſwer each other: ſo that he who gives protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hath a right to challenge Allegiance; and he that will not yield in juſt and lawful things, his Allegiance hath no right to challenge protection: therefore this penalty in the Law of nature, is neither unjuſt, nor an infringment of the liberty of the Subject; for no Subject can be imagined to be free, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the profeſſion of his allegiance, to the ſuperiour powers, who alone can give him under God protection. Fifthly, that which you call a combination &amp; confederacy, they wil judge to be the honeſt party which was true to the cauſe, and they will ſay, that the other party which deſerted the cauſe, made a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination and confederacy firſt againſt them, ſo that they were put upon a neceſſary defence to do as they did. Sixthly, they will ſay, that of neceſſity in all Nations, there muſt be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where the ſupremacy of power which is abſolute: this was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver acknowledged to be in the <hi>King,</hi> but in the Lawes which are above the <hi>King,</hi> and in the Law-making power which is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally in the Repreſentatives of the body of the Nation aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled to that effect. Theſe pleas if the matters of fact be true, and ſuch as they alledge them, are not (to a man who is diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in affection, and free to diſcern that which is equitable) alltogether irrational, but ſeeing to you and me being private men, the matters of fact are not ſo diſcernable as to oblige me to a certain belief either way, nor ſo referred, as to oblige me to become a Judge therein: therefore it is neither reaſon nor conſcience that will permit me to give a definitive ſentence ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way; but I muſt leave things above me, to the Judge who is above all, and upon the whole matter I muſt, whiles I look upon the circumſtances of civil freedom, have a care, not to looſe the liberty wherewith <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath made me free,<note place="margin">What poſture a Chriſtian ſpirit ſhould ſtand in, when civil liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are in queſtion.</note> and ſet my ſpirit above this Sea of Glaſs mingled with fire, that I may be fit to ſhew forth his praiſes, and the way of his life in all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences, whether my outward liberty be taken from me, or preſerved to me by thoſe that rule over me. And this is the poſture wherein I labor to keep my ſpirit; whether I can ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my ſelf, or not ſatisfie my ſelf, in the conſideration of civil changes; for though I cannot be ſatisfied therein by way of reaſoning, (ſeeing it is not poſſible for me to know all the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117383:11"/>of fact, and the Emergencies of councels) yet by way of acquieſcence in my duty, my Conſcience can reſt ſatisfied; and when I am come to this way of ſettlement within my ſelf, then I am free to look upon our preſent condition of liberty and ſubjection to make the beſt uſe of it I can, which is to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the nature of the changes which are come upon us, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to the councel of God, and to fit my ſelf to be ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient unto his Councel thereby. Let me then tell you what I ſeem to diſcern in our changes,<note place="margin">What the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty is which we now enjoy.</note> as to the point of liberty which gives me ſatisfaction. Firſt, we have gained the liberty for which we did fight, which was, not to be under the abſolute will of one man, in all civil concernments, and not to be under the yoaks of humane Ordinances and ſuperſtitious formalities in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious concernments. Theſe two yoaks are certainly broken, and it is apparent, that we are ſo free from them, that we have almoſt loſt all the bounds of liberty: inſomuch, that both in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and religious concernments, all the ways of order &amp; grounds of Government, are diſregarded almoſt by every one, and that without any viſible ſeverity againſt thoſe that are guilty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. As for the liberty which we fought for certainly it was not meant to be a freedom from all Lawes and Government: and where any Lawes and Government is in a Nation, there muſt needs be ſomething ſupream and abſolute, elſe there is no bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom to ſettle any thing, but all muſt run unto endleſs confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: therefore when I look upon the great paroxiſmes of chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whereinto we are fallen of late, I bleſs God, that being in a ſtate of War, we are not worſe then we are; and that although there be preſſures which in the caſe of War are unavoidable, yet that the ways of juſtice are open to find redreſs of wrongs, in caſe we will not refuſe to be true ſubjects to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it now ſtands, which is one of the intents of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement.</hi> In the preſſing whereof, I do not ſee that any point of liberty is loſt, except we will ſay, that we have a liberty, and may lawfully intend to ſtand without all <hi>Government</hi> whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and that ſuch as diſown the being of a <hi>Government,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve as well to be favoured by it, as thoſe who conſcionably and dutifully own it, which to my apprehenſion are very great incongruities. I conceive then that in this caſe of War our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117383:12"/>is preſerved as much, as poſſibly it can be in any Nation, where by force the change of <hi>Government</hi> hath been wrought. Now it is Gods counſel to bring this to paſs, that <hi>Rebellion</hi> may fall, and the deſire of all <hi>Nations</hi> come in due time, which I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from theſe <hi>Scriptures</hi> compared together, <hi>Haggai</hi> 2.5.6.21.22. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.26. and with <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7. and 11.15, 16, 17, 18, 19. and 18. <hi>per totum,</hi> and chap. 19. Theſe changes then in the councel of <hi>God</hi> prepare the way to the enjoyment of our true liberty in the Kingdom of <hi>God.</hi> Therefore I think my ſelf bound, to fit my ſelf with all diligence for the coming of the <hi>Bridegroom,</hi> ſeeking and following peace with all men, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee his face; and to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect my chief care is, to make ſtreight paths to my feet in mine own courſe, and not to turn the lame which I meet withall on my way, out of their true way, but rather to endeavor their healing, according to that meaſure of health which <hi>God</hi> hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon me, which I hold forth heartily unto you, and wiſh that you may fully enjoy it, without all ſtaggering and ſcrupuloſity.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Scruple is that the preſent power is arbitrary.</note> Your 5. ſcruple is a meer jealouſie of <hi>State,</hi> which I ſhall never ſuffer to intrench upon my <hi>Conſcience.</hi> You ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that they which are in the ſupream place of power, walk arbitrarily; I ſay it is not poſſible that the Law-making power of a <hi>Nation</hi> can walk otherwiſe, for according to their concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and arbitration of matters all things muſt be ſetled or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered. But then you ſay, if at the beginning of their inſtallment they do all with ſo high a hand;<note place="margin">The Anſwer ſhewes. That a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er muſt needs be arbitrary.</note> what will they do when they come to a full ſettlement by the conſent of all the People of the <hi>Nation?</hi> I anſwer, that I hope they will ſee the <hi>Nation</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by wholſom Lawes in a peaceable way, by ſubordinate Judicatures; and by free choſen <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> from time to time in a <hi>Parliament-way,</hi> whereunto all will be accountable of their proceedings, and I have ground to hope this, becauſe they have promiſed to endeavour it, and becauſe I ſee ſo far as I can diſcern a real proſecution of it by the making of good Lawes, and by the removal of obſtructions which ſeem to threaten a ruine of all: if the godly party would not divide, and ſtrengthen the hands of enemies, and by their diſaffected neſs and jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, did not make an Army neceſſary: this work might be ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117383:12"/>advanced:<note place="margin">That a forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble change of Government is heavier at firſt then at laſt.</note> as for the ground of your jealouſie it is not ſound; for wiſe States-men that muſt maintain a <hi>Government,</hi> or alter it upon Emergencies by force, will rule with a higher hand at the beginning then in the proſecution of a ſettlement; for in the beginning neceſſity conſtrains them to put forth the height of their power to lay the foundations of their <hi>Authority</hi> by Lawes; but when that is done, then the Lawes Rule, and are equal to all; and I am perſwaded that this, as it will be their wiſdom, ſo it is their deſign in juſtice to do, and by not refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to do my duty towards them; I make my ſelf fit in my place to be heard by ſome of them, that I may perſwade and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to proſecute their work in this way, which if I were poſſeſſed with ſuch jealouſies againſt them, as you here expreſs, I could not be able to do.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> Scruple. is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of ill uſage.</note>Your laſt objection is not a ſcruple of conſcience, why you cannot take the <hi>Engagement;</hi> but a complaint concerning the uſage of ſome who take it not, that although <hi>they are conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encious, grave, ſober, pious and peaceable men; yet they are griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and troubled, trampled upon and neglected, whilſt on the other hand, ſuch as are looſe, perverſe, Athieſts, Cavaliers and baſe wretches, are imbraced, priviledged and reſpected, only becauſe they will take the Engagement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The anſwer ſhews, that there are many cauſes of grief and complaints for want of obſerving the Rules of Chriſtianity on all ſides.</note>I confeſs it is greatly to be lamented, that this doth ſo fall out, I ſay it is to be lamented, that conſcientious and godly men, being peaceable in their affections ſhould not alſo know the way of peace; how to behave themſelves harmleſs in their actions towards the powers which God hath ſet over them, it is to be lamented, that they ſhould be ſo dealt withall by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in a time wherein we ſtand for a reformation. It is to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, that their Conſcience miſtaking its duty, ſhould occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion their grief; &amp; become upon religious grounds as to them, a cauſe of diviſion in the State. It is to be lamented laſtly, that wicked and profane men, in any Chriſtian <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> ſhould obtain more favour upon any ground whatſoever, then ſuch as are truly conſcientious and godly. Theſe evils are the ſad effects of our ſinful diſtempers, when we walk by the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of men, rather then by the Rules of <hi>Chriſtianity:</hi> for if godly, grave, pious and conſcientious men, did not make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117383:13"/>ſubſervient to a party in the State, as too many do unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly, bringing a ſnare upon their own Conſcience, by the mixture of worldly and religious conſiderations, wherein the councels of men being predominant, the ſimplicity of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is neglected: this would not fall out as it doth. But the fractions of godly men,<note place="margin">What the failings of godly men are in this kind.</note> about the particular ways of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; whereby they weaken each others hands in the main work (which is to bring all men to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to walk with him and in him, not after the fleſh but after the ſpirit) is the cauſe of all this miſchief, which <hi>God</hi> doth ſuffer to come upon his Servants, as well for a tryal of their faith and patience, as for a chaſtiſement of their misbehaviour and partial walking in the diſpenſation of his myſteries. The injuſtice of humane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions about the ways of their own framing in the holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, is juſtly puniſhable with <hi>God,</hi> by the changes of State-Governments, and the ſhaking of all humane frames therein to pieces, that nothing may remain but that which is truly ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al &amp; unmoveable.<note place="margin">What the principles &amp; practices of Stateſ-men and their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments are in this kind.</note> All States in this world, as of this world can look to nothing but to the intereſt of ſelf preſervation &amp; power over others, &amp; all the ſubordinate Agents of ſuch <hi>States</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their inſtructions, muſt look to nothing but to the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of their ſuperiors; whatſoever therefore, or whoſoever doth croſs this intereſt, and is not harmleſs and unblameable towards them in point of ſecurity; they think it juſt (and rationally they cannot be blamed for thinking ſo) that they ought to remove both it and him out of their way; and whatſoevr and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is (profeſſedly at leaſt) faithful to them in point of ſecurity; they take hold of and cheriſh both it and him. Nor can they as true <hi>States-men</hi> look to any thing elſe but this; all other Relations or contemplations of mens qualities, are drowned and ſwollowed up in this one conſideration, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yea or no he be to be truſted, and is like to prove faithful to this their intereſt: if they get aſſurance of this, the worldly wiſdom of a State looks no further; but if they can get no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of this, all other conſiderations whatſoever are laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and the more eminent men are in parts, or in eſteem and repute for godlineſs, they become the greater objects of State-jealouſies, if they will give them no aſſurance of their fidelity;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117383:13"/>and this I conceive is the reaſon why godly and conſciencious men, are troubled by the Inſtruments of State-ſecurity and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who are baſe wretches, and men void of all grace, are che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by them.<note place="margin">The Remedy to be uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe evills, and the grounds thereof.</note> If then you and other godly men could be brought upon rational and religious grounds to give the State wherein you live, and the Rulers thereof, that ſecurity, which may take off the edge of their jealouſie, that you are not an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to their temporal ſtanding and ſafety, and that you ſhall not be acceſſary to any practiſes which tend to the overthrow of a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> Intereſt, I make no doubt but the cauſe of your complaint, and with it many publick evills would ceaſe: and why you ſhould not give them this ſecurity, truly I can diſcern no ground for it, neither in reference to Chriſtianity nor Morality. For in morality as you are a Subject,<note place="margin">In reſpect of Morality.</note> and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live ſafely, nor enjoy any outward benefit of the life of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture here without the protection of the <hi>Government</hi> which is over this State, you are bound in gratitude towards thoſe that manage it; for their pains in watching and looking to publick ſafety to own them in their places, and if you will not own them, when without them you cannot enjoy any ſecurity, you are not only unthankful but unjuſt, for by not owning them in the power whereof they are fully poſſeſt for the good of all you do what in you lieth to diſſolve the bond of publick ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which in all Subjects is nothing elſe but the owning of a <hi>Government</hi> by a profeſſed ſubjection thereunto in things good and lawful: nor can any man rationally alledge any ground why he ought not to own the powers which are actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally over him by doing the things commanded by them, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be one of theſe three: Either that he doth own another power, inconſiſtent with the power which is over him, in the place where he lives; or that he will own no power at all in humane ſocieties; or that he ſees cauſe to except againſt the things commanded as unlawful in themſelves.</p>
            <p>The firſt exception to own another power inconſiſtent with the power which is over him, a priſoner of War may make to thoſe that have taken him priſoner, and an Ambaſſador from a forrain Nation, towards thoſe to whom he is ſent.</p>
            <p>But if he owns neither another power, nor that which is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him, then he muſt own no Magiſtracy amongſt men, nor Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117383:14"/>at all: for this conſequence as I conceive, is unavoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. If I will not own the powers which are over me, I muſt either own other powers inconſiſtent with theſe, or none at all; if I own other powers inconſiſtent with theſe, I ought to ſeek protection from thoſe, and not from theſe, and am bound to ſet thoſe up againſt theſe and conſequently have no right to any common benefit from theſe. But if I wil own no Magiſtracy at all, then no Magiſtracy ought to own me; nor have I any right to live in any humane ſociety, for no ſociety can be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the exception doth lie againſt the lawfulneſs of the things commanded, then he muſt ſay, that it is unlawful for a ſubject to promiſe that he will be true and faithful to the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi> wherein he liveth, becauſe the form of <hi>Government</hi> thereof, is not the ſame which it was before, which is an aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo irrational that I conceive no man will own it, nor can any man lawfully enter into any promiſe or obligation to God or men, which can make this <hi>Commandement</hi> void. Let all ſoules be ſubject to the powers that are over them: therefore it is altogether inconſiſtent with morality, that a Subject in things good and lawful, ſhould not promiſe ſubmiſſion to the powers which are over him, which I conceive is yet more then what the <hi>Engagement</hi> in expreſs tearms doth require of you.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> beſides that which I have ſaid already concerning the freedom of your Conſcience,<note place="margin">In reſpect of Chriſtianity.</note> which is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of any outward worldly things: I ſhall only mention this clear rule given to all men as they are men, which to my underſtanding is beyond all exception: it is the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Command, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers, I ſay then, that no ſoule (that is no man) may as a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> exempt it ſelf from being ſubject in things good and lawful to the jurisdiction which is over it; and although this tranſlation will bear the weight of this inference, yet the words may be rendered more properly and meerly to their full ſenſe thus. Let every ſoule be ſubordinate to the powers which have the eminency over them, for the original words <hi>hupotaſſeſthay</hi> is properly to be ſubordinate;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and <hi>exouſiai huperechouſai</hi> are powers having ſuperiority or eminency: and thus the laſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117383:14"/>
               <hi>Dutch</hi> Tranſlation doth render the words;<note place="margin">Alle ziele zy den mach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten over haer geſtelt onder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worpen. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Let every ſoule be ſubmitted to the powers which are ſetled over them, as for the ordinary exception which is brought in to limit the generality of this Rule, that the word <hi>exouſia</hi> doth ſignifie only a lawful power, it is of no validity at all, for both in heathen and in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred writings it is taken in the ſence which ſignifies any ability and the power of force; look upon <hi>Scapula</hi> in the compounds of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and he will tell you that <hi>Plutarch</hi> and <hi>Herodian</hi> do joyn <hi>exouſian</hi> and <hi>dunamin</hi> as words of the ſame ſence,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> &amp; that it is uſed generally for any thing that a man can do, whether law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully or unlawfully: as in <hi>Xenophon</hi> you have this expreſſion <hi>exouſian echo cleptein,</hi> that is, I have power to ſteal.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Here then the word cannot be taken for a lawful, but only for a licencious power: that is, for an ability to do a thing unlawful: and in the Scripture ſo far as I can now call to mind, I find it taken more in this ſence then in any other, <hi>exouſia touſcotous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the power of darkneſs, when <hi>Judas</hi> did lay violent hands upon his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſter, as upon a robber and a thief, I ſuppoſe you will not ſay he had a lawfull warrant to do, and <hi>Colloſ.</hi> 1.13. the ſame expreſſion is uſed to deſcribe the power which the Devill hath over our ſoules in corrupt nature, which I do not think you wil call a juſt authority uſed by him,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and <hi>Luke</hi> 22.25. <hi>exouſiazontes</hi> is to exerciſe might and force which is the proper Character of the Rulers of the Nations, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> forbids his Diſciples to affect: ſo alſo 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.12. <hi>exouſiaſtheſomai</hi> is to be under might and a forcible conſtraint without freedom;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the word then in Scripture phraſe is, as in Heathen Authors, the power of force as well if not more then of right. And in general it is an ability to do what one will which is indeed proper to ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, for ſuch as have an uncontrouleable power in acting, are ſuperiour powers, intimating that where God doth put any in a place of ſuch eminency above others, that they can do what they will without controule; there all men under them, are to ſubmit unto them in things good and lawful: now if men whom you call grave, pious, and conſcientious, will not take notice of this Rule conſcionably and piouſly, to obey their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers for Gods ſake; I muſt leave them to the event which <hi>God</hi> will determine over them, and be ſorry that they underſtand
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117383:15"/>not their duty, and the rule of that freedom by which they ſtand under their ſuperiours.</p>
            <p>Thus I have given you my thoughts concerning your ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, which I beſeech the Lord to manifeſt unto you, ſo far as they are his truths, and wherein they are not ſuch, I beſeech him to let me ſee the error of them: for I am far from any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intereſt in them, then as they are the teſtimonies of righteouſneſs without prejudice, and without partiality. I ſhal be glad to hear from you what your ſence thereof is, how far you are ſatisfied thereby. The Lord inſtruct us and give us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in all things, and teach us to profit by all his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, to his grace I commend you and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written at St. James</hi> 
                  <date> this 9. <hi>June,</hi> 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your faithful and affectionate Friend and Brother in Chriſt, <hi>JOHN DURY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
